<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on The Pro Amateur</title>
    <link>https://mmozgovoy.dev/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on The Pro Amateur</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 26 Feb 2022 13:13:40 +0900</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://mmozgovoy.dev/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>🎤 Some Reflections on War and Future</title>
      <link>https://mmozgovoy.dev/posts/some-reflections-on-war-and-future/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Feb 2022 13:13:40 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mmozgovoy.dev/posts/some-reflections-on-war-and-future/</guid>
      <description>A vague title of this piece is deliberate: there is no single clear message I am going to send, but I think I am ought to express some feelings and share my thoughts on the ongoing events. In most cases I am inclined to let the things settle down and discuss them later, as I am quite a slow thinker, and it takes time for any consistent picture to form in my head.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>🧪 The Art of Titles</title>
      <link>https://mmozgovoy.dev/posts/the-art-of-titles/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Dec 2021 11:13:40 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mmozgovoy.dev/posts/the-art-of-titles/</guid>
      <description>A few weeks ago we had a lab meeting, where a student was presenting his summary of a paper he had read earlier. While in general his talk was OK, it was obvious he had difficulties extracting the essence of the paper. His talk was based on a fairly accurate section-by-section summary of the original text, so it was hard for us to figure out which of these parts really captured the authors&amp;#39; primary contribution.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>🔧 DIY Minesweeper Board Game</title>
      <link>https://mmozgovoy.dev/posts/diy-minesweeper/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Dec 2021 15:11:50 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mmozgovoy.dev/posts/diy-minesweeper/</guid>
      <description>Intro Let’s have a less serious post this time for a change. Today I will explain how to create your own Minesweeper board game from simple materials, mostly cardboard.
 Surprisingly, an obvious idea of creating a sort of &amp;#34;real-life&amp;#34; version of Minesweeper has left little trace on the net. I can mention a couple of projects like Post-it Minesweeper and Minesweeper with tactile interface. The first approach is cute, but it’s really just a one-time fun; the second one is a bit too large-scale and serious, and it relies on electronics.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>🧪 Why Go To Statement Considered Harmful?</title>
      <link>https://mmozgovoy.dev/posts/why-go-to-considered-harmful/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Nov 2021 10:13:40 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mmozgovoy.dev/posts/why-go-to-considered-harmful/</guid>
      <description>A Quick Intro I needed to cite Dijkstra’s famous 1968 letter the other day, and finally had an easy chance to read it through. It would have been shame not to do it, given its modest size.
 There are many &amp;#34;folk beliefs&amp;#34; in our trade, as Bossavit’s book shows, that turn out to have quite a weak foundation. Currently, the &amp;#34;go to debate&amp;#34; is not on the table at all, as most modern languages have abandoned this operation (and it is used very sparingly anyway even when it is available).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>⚙️ Visual Studio Code: Python Setup</title>
      <link>https://mmozgovoy.dev/posts/vs-code-python-setup/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Oct 2021 10:11:50 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mmozgovoy.dev/posts/vs-code-python-setup/</guid>
      <description>The Python Experience It took me a while to sit down and write this post, because I was actively experimenting with the VS Code setup for Python. I used it before, naturally, but having to write about something forces me to do my homework and make sure there are no obvious flaws in the suggestions I propose. Thus, I had to double-check all the tools and extensions I use for Python, and confirm that my setup is current.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>⚙️ Visual Studio Code Setup</title>
      <link>https://mmozgovoy.dev/posts/vs-code-setup/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Oct 2021 10:11:43 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mmozgovoy.dev/posts/vs-code-setup/</guid>
      <description>Choosing the Editor As I mentioned in one of my previous notes, an integrated development environment is something very natural for me. I feel more comfortable using &amp;#34;the whole package&amp;#34; rather than thinking about compiling, linking, debugging, profiling, UI building, etc. as about separate activities requiring separate tools. And yet, the &amp;#34;IDE approach&amp;#34; isn’t universal. I can’t have a full-fledged IDE for every language I use, and I don’t really need all the tools related to this or that technology.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>💡 Matryoshka Architecture</title>
      <link>https://mmozgovoy.dev/posts/matryoshka-architecture/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Sep 2021 01:06:31 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mmozgovoy.dev/posts/matryoshka-architecture/</guid>
      <description>One of the Faces of Complexity Today I am planning to write on a topic that is addressed literally in every book on software engineering. Yet I believe that too many projects (including my own) need more attention to some of the most basic ways of fighting complexity. Complexity is, yeah, a complex phenomenon, discussed in numerous sources, including a highly influential Brooks’s No Silver Bullet essay. Recently I wrote about Black, which insists on code made up of short lines.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>💡 Representing the World with Objects: a Telling Exercise</title>
      <link>https://mmozgovoy.dev/posts/representing-the-world-with-objects/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Sep 2021 23:11:40 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mmozgovoy.dev/posts/representing-the-world-with-objects/</guid>
      <description>The Adventure Begins I am not happy with this title, but the whole topic popped up a bit suddenly, and I decided to jot down some thoughts, while they are still fresh. It is going to be a little story about a very innocuous-looking tiny exercise that turned out to be more difficult than I anticipated, and thus made me thinking about the hardships of translating our common language into programming language concepts, say, using OOP.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>⚙️ Experiencing Black</title>
      <link>https://mmozgovoy.dev/posts/experiencing-black/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Sep 2021 15:11:43 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mmozgovoy.dev/posts/experiencing-black/</guid>
      <description>On Code and Formatting Styles One of my long-term goals is to setup a powerful development environment that would make the most of today’s technology. As someone who grew up using QuickBasic and C++Builder, I could never understand deliberate efforts to rely on simple text editors and command-line compilers. To me, it is like claiming that the past 20 or 30 years of toolmaking gave us nothing worthy of attention.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>⚙️ Managing Python with Poetry</title>
      <link>https://mmozgovoy.dev/posts/managing-python-with-poetry/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Sep 2021 14:47:03 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mmozgovoy.dev/posts/managing-python-with-poetry/</guid>
      <description>The Problem Python is a very reasonable &amp;#34;default&amp;#34; language of choice for a variety of tasks. At least on desktop platforms, it makes sense to start with Python and see how it goes. Unfortunately, along its way to popularity it lost much of the simplicity that made it fun in the first place. An especially egregious aspect of Python is its poor backward compatibility. In practice it means that your codebase will only reliably work with a specific version of Python interpreter.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
